U.S. Department of Labor Wage and Hour and Public Contracts Division 5320
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
U.S. Department of Labor Wage and Hour and Public Contracts Division
1944-1964
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
U.S. Department of Labor
5320
3 cubic feet
3 linear ft.
Proceedings.
This group contains the economic reports prepared by the Bureau of Labor Statistics for the various minimum wage boards.
2294709
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, April 22, 2014
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 11, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The Secretary of Labor is responsible for the enforcement of the Fair Labor Standards Act, and certain administrative functions which are supplementary. One of these functions is to establish minimum wages (which may be below the minimums generally required by law) for industries in Puerto Rico. The Secretary delegated this responsibility to the Wage-Hour Administrator.
Wage order proceedings are initiated by the Secretary, published in the Federal Register, giving notice of hearings by industry committees to recommend the minimum rate to be paid employees engaged in commerce or in the production of goods for commerce.
These orders will contain a definition of the particular industry and make provision for convening the committee. The committee will be composed of an equal number of persons representing the industry the employees and the public, one of whom has been designated the chairman.
Each committee will be furnished a lawyer to serve as committee counsel, and an economist to advise and assist the committee. The administrator also prepares an economic report containing such data as he is able to assemble pertinent to the matters to be referred to the committee. Hearings are held by the committee and after the issues are resolved, it issues a report, containing findings of fact and recommendations. The secretary then publishes these recommendations. The secretary then publishes these recommendations and provides by order that they shall become effective 15 days thereafter.
Scope and Contents
Specifically, includes a copy of a letter from Francis O'Neill (chairman, National Mediation Board) to President Richard M. Nixon declaring that an emergency existed and enclosing a proposed draft of an executive order to create the Emergency Board to deal with the dispute; the final executive order creating the Board; Board hearings (3 vol.); numerous labor and management exhibits filed with the Board, including a statement by William Winpisinger (vice-president, International Association of Machinists) describing work done by his members who worked for railroads; and a copy of the Board's award.
Also various documents on previous shopcraft disputes including a copy of a U.S. Department of Labor publication, THE RAILROAD SHOPCRAFT FACTFINDING STUDY (1968) as well as copies of agreements between the following parties: National Railway Labor Conference and Eastern, Western and Southeastern Carriers Conference Committees and employees of such carriers, represented by the organizations comprising the Railway Employes Department, AFL-CIO (1964); railroads represented by the Eastern, Western and Southeastern Carriers Conference Committee and employees of such railroads represented by the Employees National Conference Committees of eleven cooperating railway labor organizations (1960); and carriers represented by the National Railway Conference and Regional Carrier Conference Committees and the International Association of Machinists, the Sheet Metal Workers, the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers, and the International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders, Blacksmiths, Forgers and Helpers (1969).
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5321: U.S. Department of Labor Wage and Hour and Public Contracts Division Special Industry Committee #12 Records 5322: U.S. Department of Labor Wage and Hour and Public Contracts Division Special Industry Committee #13 Records 5323: U.S. Department of Labor Wage and Hour and Public Contracts Division Special Industry Committee #14 Records 5324: U.S. Department of Labor Wage and Hour and Public Contracts Division Special Industry Committee #15 Records 5325: U.S. Department of Labor Wage and Hour and Public Contracts Division Special Industry Committee #16 Records 5326: U.S. Department of Labor Wage and Hour and Public Contracts Division Special Industry Committee #31 Records
Arbitration, Industrial -- United States -- Cases.; Job evaluation -- United States.; Railroad -- Employees; Seward, Ralph T. (Ralph Theodore), 1907-; Winpisinger, William W.; United States. Department of Labor.; International Association of Machinists.; United States. Emergency Board No. 176.
2294709
- The Alcoholic Beverage and Industrial Alcohol Industry in Puerto Rico, 1952-1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- The Artificial Flower, Decoration and Party Favor Industry in Puerto Rico, 1950-1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- The Banking, Insurance and Finance Industry in Puerto Rico, 1950-1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- The Boot and Shoe Industry, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- The Button, Buckle and Jewelry Industry in Puerto Rico., 1944-1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- The Cement Industry in Puerto Rico, 1950-1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Chemical, Petroleum, Rubber and Related Products Industry in Puerto Rico, 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- The Children's Dress and Related Products Industry in Puerto Rico, 1956-1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Children's Dress and Related Products Industry in Puerto Rico, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- The Cigar and Cigarette Industry in Puerto Rico, 1941-1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- The Clay and Clay Products Industry, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Fabricated Plastic Products Industry in Puerto Rico, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Scope and Contents
  November 1960
- Electrical, Instrument and Related Products Industry in Puerto Rico, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  July 1957
- Communications, Utilities, and Transport Industry in Puerto Rico, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  April - September 1962
- Construction, Business Service, Motion Picture and Miscellaneous Industry in Puerto Rico, 1951-1962 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  December 1951 - July 1962
- Fabric and Leather Glove Industry in Puerto Rico, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  April 1956
- Foods, Beverages and Related Products Industries, 1951-1962 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- The Fruit and Vegetable Packing and Farm Products Assembling Industry, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  August 26 1943
- Gloves and Mittens Industry. Transcripts of Public Hearing and Oral Argument., 1942 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  March and April 1942
- Digest of Transcript. Grain Products Industry, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- The Hairnet Industry of Puerto Rico, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  April 18 1944
- Handkerchief Manufacturing Industry, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  August 1942
- Handkerchief, Square Scarf and Art Linen Industry, 1957-1962 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- The Hat Industry (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Hooked Rug Industry in Puerto Rico, 1947-1955 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Hosiery Industry in Puerto Rico, 1942-1957 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Jewel Cutting and Polishing Industry, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  May 1951
- The Leaf Tobacco Industry in Puerto Rico, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  January 1952
- Leather, Leather Goods, Shoe and Related Products Industry in Puerto Rico, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  December 1956
- Lumber and Wood Products Industry, 1951-1960 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Manufacturing and Miscellaneous Industry in Puerto Rico, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  July 1961
- Men's and Boys' Clothing and Related Products Industry, 1953-1962 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Metal Hair Accessories Industry, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  December 1955
- Metal, Plastics, Machinery, Instrument, Transportation Equipment and Allied Industries in Puerto Rico, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  January 1953
- Metal, Machinery, Transportation and Allied Products Industry, 1956-1960 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Metal Ore, Coal, Petroleum and Natural Gas Extraction Industry, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  September 1943
- Miscellaneous Apparel Industry, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  August and October 1941
- Needle Work and Fabricated Textile Products Industry in Puerto Rico, 1944-1962 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Paper, Paper Products, Printing and Publishing Industry in Puerto Rico, 1951-1960 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- The Shoe Manufacturing Industry in Puerto Rico, 1951-1960 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Stone, Clay, Glass, Cement and Related Products Industry in Puerto Rico, 1957-1963 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Stone, Glass and Related Products Industry, 1952-1956 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  May 1952 - November 1956
- Straw, Hair and Related Products Industry in Puerto Rico, 1957-1962 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Sugar and Related Products Industry, 1942-1964 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Sugar Manufacturing and Alcoholic Beverages Industry in Puerto Rico, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  October 4 1962
- Sugar Manufacturing Industry in Puerto Rico, 1952-1962 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Sweater and Knit Swimwear Industry in Puerto Rico, 1957-1962 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Textile and Textile Products Industry in Puerto Rico, 1938-1962 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Textile and Textile Products Industry in Puerto Rico, 1941-1962 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- The Tobacco Industry in Puerto Rico, 1955-1961 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Vegetable, Fruit, Nut-Packing and Processing Industry in Puerto Rico, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  December 1949
- Wholesaling, Warehousing and Other Distribution Industries in Puerto Rico, 1947-1963 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Women's and Children's Underwear Industry, 1956-1960 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- The Woolen Industry (Box 3, Folder 15)